I've been coming to Jungto Society
for more than a year now.
This is my third question to you.
Thanks to you, I no longer have
any grudge against my parents.
I actually have been regretting
how I'd hated them in the past.
Nowadays, I often feel unsure of myself
because I don't like who I am.
Last time I spoke to you, you said
that I have a very strong self-image.
When I look into myself, I notice guilt
deeply entrenched in my subconscious.
I see myself judging, critizing,
and suppressing myself.
How can I come to accept myself
as I am and be at ease with myself?
(Sunim) There are a lot of I's, the I who critizes
you, the I who regrets, the I who watches you.
(Audience Laughter)
Buddha says there is no I,
but you created many of them.
(Audience Laughter)
Don't complicate things and keep making the I
who watches and the I who is being watched.
I see, but it's difficult to practice
that even when I understand it.
As you said earlier,
you hated your mother in the past.
But you prayed with gratitude toward your parents
and noticed many good things they did for you.
You learned that you hated them for foolish reasons.
And it should have ended there.
If you criticize yourself for your past hatred,
then you are shifting the blame to yourself.
You hated your mother in the past
because of your foolishness.
You can acknowledge
your past foolishness and end it there.
Instead, you continue to blame
yourself for your past actions.
Hating your parents does not amount to spiritual
practice. Neither does critizing yourself.
You held grudge against your parents
because they did not meet your expectations.
You have very strong expectations
for yourself.
So you cannot accept
the person you are in reality.
You should not create these ideal images
of who you should be.
That is all false expectation.
This angry and irritable person
is the real you, not the false image.
Thinking "I shouldn't be angry, I shouldn't
be this or that" is having false expectations.
Stop telling yourself
that you should be this or that.
Just notice that you're being angry
when that happens.
Just notice that you're
being angry or hateful.
Do these emotions happen because of
other people or because of yourself?
They come from your own ignorance.
So just notice that you're upset.
Don't hate yourself for being upset.
Just as you don't hate others for being angry,
don't hate yourself for being angry.
Because you tell yourself that you shouldn't be
angry, you hate yourself for being angry.
Don't tell yourself that you should be this or that.
Don't limit yourself to what you
think a spiritual practitioner should be.
A spiritual practitioner is one
who is aware of him or herself.
Just be aware of yourself and let it go.
A spiritual practitioner is a self-aware person.
She does not criticize herself.
If you trip and fall, you just pick yourself up.
Why blame yourself for falling?
You blame yourself when
you think you shouldn't fall.
Just be aware of yourself
tripping and falling.
If you fall again, just notice.
Don't make trouble with yourself for falling.
(Questioner) I understand that in
my head, but it's hard to practice that.
That's why it's called practice.
You know you should quit smoking.
But it's hard to do that in reality.
You need simply to notice your desire to smoke
and let it go, instead of getting caught up with it.
You seem to be getting caught up
with your thoughts.
You keep focusing on the idea that you must be
this or that, so when you can't, you blame yourself.
Let it go.
Don't define or limit
yourself in such a way.
Just notice yourself as things happen.
You created a certain image for yourself and
keep trying to force yourself to be that person.
You tell yourself that you should be a certain way
because you've practiced for over a year now.
And when you can't be
that person, you hate yourself.
Do you think your life has improved
since a year ago?
(Questioner) I'm much better now.
Great, that doesn't mean
you should stop here.
We are constantly practicing.
You've changed from a very
irritable person in the past.
Now you're a little less
irritable and angry.
But you're not yet completely free
from anger and hatred.
When you look back, you do notice
that you've become less angry.
You should feel great about
that positive change.
Look at how much you've
changed for the better.
Don't dwell on how you're still angry.
Be proud of how much you've improved.
At the same time, as you haven't reached
your goal yet, keep practicing.
So how should I pray in the morning?
It depends on what your
goals are right now.
There is no separate prayer for your situation.
It's the same for your practice.
Our practice says that all suffering
comes from within ourselves.
Every time you suffer is
an opportunity for practice.
Practice is knowing that your anger and sadness
come from within yourself, not others.
What is your problem
these days? You're sad?
I just feel depressed sometimes.
So I'm asking. Do you have depression?
I used to take medicine for depression
and see doctors for it. I now feel better.
But every once in a while, I feel depressed.
This happens more often during seasonal
changes. Be careful during these times.
If you become depressed while sitting down,
get up immediately and start moving around.
Take a bath, or go for a walk.
Don't get sucked into depressing thoughts.
If you think too much, you'll fall into a trap.
In times like that, just get up and go outside
for a jog or walk. Watch TV or do prostrations.
Don't fall into those thoughts. They are
like quicksands. You can fall very quickly.
Then the depressing thoughts
appear quite like reality.
You have to snap out of it quickly.
When you meditate, it's easy
to let your mind wander.
Then you come back to yourself
by focusing on your breath.
You repeat this countless times--you wander
and come back, wander and come back.
It's the same thing. You have to
practice coming back to yourself.
Depression will pull you down deeper
and deeper into negative thoughts.
Then you can get to a point where you
think there's no reason to keep living.
And then feel a sudden impulse
to jump out the window.
But if the phone rings as you're climbing
the window, you forget all about your thoughts.
(Audience Laughter)
Such a sudden change in your mind.
Such a short moment can make a big
difference. Don't get stuck in those thoughts.
Thank you.
(Applause)